I'd like to ask a few ladies about the fact that I've organized a
xin vài cô là ở nhà tôi là đã tổ chức
repentance ceremony for Buddhists at home on the 14th of the month.
cho các phật tử sám hối 1430 tại nhà thế
However, I want to ask the lady for an example: when listening to
nhưng tôi muốn bài Cô là ví dụ bây giờ
Dharma teachings, I can schedule the time.
nghe pháp thì có thể Cái thời gian nghe
For example, if the lady is giving a lecture today,
pháp tôi nghe lịch giờ đi mà ví dụ hôm
but maybe tomorrow evening
nay cô giảng nhưng mà có thể tầm tối mai
around 7:00, we can all listen together. Is
khoảng 700 Chúng tôi nghe cùng với nhau
that okay, or do we have to listen at the
thì thế có được không hay là phải nghe
exact time, like today at
đúng cái thời điểm mà hôm nay phát lúc
8:00, so we listen at 8:00 for the lady's guidance? Dear fellow practitioners,
800 thì là sẽ nghe 8 gi bài cô để cô chỉ
every
dạy Kính thưa quý đạo hữu mỗi một cái
small thing has its own karmic connection. If the
việc nhỏ nhất nó có nhân duyên thế nếu
Dharma group agrees not to
như đạo tràng mà thống nhất là không
listen on the 3rd, 10th, and 20th of the month, then we must
nghe vào mùng 3 và 10 mùng 20 thì phải
find a fixed day, not
tìm một ngày cố định chứ đừng là chúng
listen whenever we feel like it. If we listen whenever we feel like it,
ta thích thì nghe lúc này không thích
our hearts seeking the Dharma won't have the merit to seek the
của chúng ta nó không có nổi cái Phước
Dharma. For example,
cầu pháp các quý đạo hữu ạ ví dụ như là
the evenings of the 3rd and 20th are for the club.
tối mùng 3 và tối 20 là của câu lạc bộ
If we can listen there, that's best because
Nếu nghe được thì tốt nhất vì trong đó
it fosters harmony with the Buddhists in the
nó có Lục Hòa với các phật tử trong câu
club. That's the best option. But
lạc bộ Thì cái đó nó là tốt nhất thế Còn
if...  But if we're talking about people who are working,
nếu như mà lại ống vào toàn người đi làm
for example, we'll choose
chẳng hạn thì chúng ta sẽ chọn vào ngày
Saturday or Sunday evenings. But we
tối thứ bảy hay tối chủ nhật thế nhưng
have to listen on fixed evenings.
mà phải nghe vào những tối cố định thì
Why do I say those fixed evenings? It's so that we can
tại sao lại nói là những cái tối cố định
eliminate
đấy là để cho mình tự gạt đi những cái
our lazy minds. At that specific time, on that specific day, we must
mình đúng đến giờ đấy đúng đến ngày đấy
listen so that our minds are
là phải nghe thì cái tâm mình nó nhất
focused on the Buddha's teachings. Then, when
hướng đến với phật pháp Thế thì đến lúc
we say, "I pray to the Buddha, I wholeheartedly rely on,
mình mới bạch cái câu này con bạch Phật
learn, and seek the
con một lòng nhất tâm nương tựa học hỏi
Buddha's teachings," that's a truthful statement, and
cầu Phật pháp nó là câu nói chân thật và
it has its fixed power.
nó có cái năng lực cố định của nó thế
But if you say, "I pray whenever I'm free, I don't
còn nếu các chị dỗi lúc nào thì tu không
practice whenever I'm not free," you'll
dỗi lúc nào thì tu thì các chị không bao
never be able to make that statement. And
giờ có được cái câu bạch đấy và cái Bạch
that statement is also incorrect; it
Thế nó cũng không không không đúng nó
doesn't generate merit and has no
không sinh ra cái Phước báo mà chả có
power. If you say, "I pray to the
năng lực gì thì các chị bạch là con bạch
Buddha, at first I'm free, I listen,"
Phật lúc đầu dỗi thì con nghe th Thế thì
it doesn't work. If you're free, you practice, if you're busy, you
nó không được rồi dỗi thì tu bận thì con
rest. That hasn't yet generated the
nghỉ Thế thì nó chưa ra được một cái
power of the Dharma.
năng lực của Pháp Các chị hiểu nó ra một
Remember, this is the
cái năng lực nhớ này cái cái cái công
power of the Golden Chrysanthemum Club.  This is
đức của của câu lạc bộ cúc vàng không
n't just for you, but for
phải dành cho em mà dành cho tất cả
everyone who practices the Six
những người nào thực hành đúng pháp Lục
Harmonies correctly, because that merit is not
Hòa tại vì cái công đức đó nó không phải
limited, it's immeasurable. So whoever
là cạn mà nó là vô lượng cho nên ai thực
practices the Six Harmonies correctly will also
hành đúng Lục Hòa thì người đó cũng Bạch
receive it. I wholeheartedly practice the Six Harmonies
được con nay một lòng thực hành pháp Lục
at the Golden Chrysanthemum Club at the Dharma
Hòa tại câu lạc bộ cúc vàng tại đạo
center. Therefore, I dedicate this merit of
tràng Thế cho nên con xin hồi hướng cái
practicing the Six Harmonies to this or
công đức tu Lục Hòa này cho việc này
that cause, so that cause will all receive the
việc kia thì cái việc đó nó đều được cái
blessings of the Six Harmonies.
Phước của Lục Hòa cái sự thực hành tinh
My diligent practice and the diligent practice
nghiêm của em và thực hành tinh nghiêm
of the other sisters will both
của các chị thì hai cái lời hồi hướng
receive equal blessings, no different from
đều có phước báu bằng nhau không khác
the esteemed ones. Do you understand this point? It's not that the
các quý đầ u rõ chỗ này chưa chứ không
dedication by the club leader is necessarily better than
phải cô chủ nhiệm hồi hướng chắc là hơn
mine; it's not the same because that
mình không phải nó như nhau vì cái công
merit is created together,
đức đó chúng ta cùng nhau tạo ra mỗi
each person has their own circumstances, but
người mỗi duyên cùng nhau tạo ra nhưng
whoever practices most diligently will
ai thực hành tinh Nghiêm nhất thì người
receive the most from it. It
đó lấy được ở trong đó ra nhiều nhất Nó
's a precious treasure. Do you understand this point?
là cái kho quý đầu Hữu rõ chỗ này chưa
And that blessing is immeasurable because the
và cái phước đấy nó vô lượng bởi vì công
merit of the Six Harmonies is the merit of all
đức Lục Hòa này là công đức của cả Chư
Buddhas, not just of
Phật Phật chứ không phải riêng gì mấy
us few people. So whoever
con người chúng ta đâu nhá đấy thì ai
practices the Six Harmonies diligently will receive the most.  Then
thực hành tinh Nghiêm Lục Hòa thì người
everyone will receive that blessing,
đó đều lấy được cái Phước Đó ra đấy các
dear fellow practitioners. Don't you see? It's not just Uncle Hoan Quan who receives it.
quý đạo hữu Thấy hay không chứ đâu có
So, Buddhist follower Oanh, who is in a new Dharma center, has only been
nên là phật tử Oanh ở mới đạo tràng mới
active for
thôi mới hoạt động được bao nhiêu lâu
about 6
đâu mới tách ra thì khoảng được 6 B
months, just separated from the center. The same goes for the Buddhist followers in the
tháng nay thôi kể cả các phật tử ở trong
team. If we truly practice the Six Harmonies, when we
đội tráng cũng thế Nếu thực Hoành Lục
encounter a critical situation, we only face danger. I am a disciple, my
chỉ gặp cái lúc nguy cấp con là Đệ tử
name is this, I practice in
con tên thế này con tu tập ở trong đạo
this Dharma center, this center belongs to the
tràng này đạo tràng này thuộc câu lạc bộ
Golden Cup Club of Ba Vang Temple. I joyfully
cốc vàng chùa Ba Vàng con hoan hỉ thực
practice the Six Harmonies Dharma. Now my family is
hành pháp Lục Hòa đến nay gia đình con
facing this critical situation, I pray to the
gặp cái việc nguy cấp này con xin cầu
Buddha for blessings and dedicate the merit of the Six Harmonies Dharma
Phật gia hội cho con xin hồi hướng cái
to this matter so that it
công đức Lục Hòa cho con vào việc này nó
will transform, dear fellow practitioners. That is due to
có chuyển hóa các quý đạo hữu ạ Đấy là
ourselves, due to the merit of our sincere devotion, dear fellow
do mình do cái công đức tến tâm của mình
practitioners. So, to help you
các quý đạo hữu ạ Thế để cho các quý đạo
understand, the merit and blessings of the
hữu hiểu rõ là công đức Phước báo của
Six Harmonies Dharma are very great. Encountering this
Lục Hòa rất là lớn trên chúng ta gặp
Dharma is very rare from countless
được Pháp là rất là hy hữu từ vô lượng
eons until now, so let's diligently
kiếp đến giờ cho nên chúng ta chăm chỉ
practice. Whoever practices will benefit.
thực hành ai thực hành thì người có lợi
There are some  A question from Minh Hau Buddhist Group: "
nha có một số câu hỏi của Đạo Tràng Minh
Reverend, please guide us on
Hậu à Thưa cô chỉ dạy cho chúng em là
how a group leader should teach and instruct the Buddhist followers in the group to
có các phật tử cùng ban như thế nào để
best perform their duties and generate merit.
làm phận sự phát sinh công đức tốt nhất
I sincerely appreciate your guidance.
Em xin chân công đức chỉ dạy của cô tức
As the leader of a group in our Buddhist community, for
là người trưởng ban trong đạo tràng của
example, the leader of the
mình ấy hả thì người trưởng ban ví dụ
ritual group, if there are any
như là ban nghi lễ chẳng hạn thế có cái
issues or questions, please bring them to the management
vấn đề gì chưa Hiểu chưa hỏi thì đưa lên
committee for discussion. Then, if there are any
ban CN sự của mình ấy tham khảo với nhau
remaining
xong rồi thì còn cái vấn đề gì nó khúc
difficulties, bring them to the executive committee.
mắc thì đưa lên ban điều hành nhá Thế
Also, when fellow practitioners establish new Buddhist groups,
còn khi mà các đạo hữu lập các đạo tràng
the ritual group will directly
mới này thì cái ban nghi lễ sẽ trực tiếp
guide them. If there's
hướng dẫn cho ở trong cái nhóm của mình
anything you need, please write it down
có cái gì thì các quý đạo hữu cứ họ viết
and ask: 'We need guidance on the
vào đó để hỏi là chúng tôi cần hướng dẫn
consecration ceremony,' 'We need guidance on
Nghi Lễ an vị Chúng tôi cần hướng dẫn
the funeral ceremony,' 'We need
cái nghi lễ đám ma Chúng tôi cần hướng
guidance on any other ceremony,' and the guidance committee
dẫn nghi lễ gì thì cái ban hướng dẫn của
will provide
mình sẽ hướng dẫn cho các quý đạo hữu
complete instruction. Therefore,
một cách đầy đủ nhá Cho nên là trưởng
while the group leader learns, they
ban học hỏi nhưng mà trưởng ban thì cũng
cannot fail to consult with the group
không thể không bàn bạc với đạo tràng
leader. That is, all matters
trưởng đâu nhá Tức là tất cả mọi việc
of the groups are discussed and understood."  We must discuss this with the Dharma
của các ban đều phải bàn bạc với đạo
leader, then reach a consensus, and then
tràng trưởng sau đó thống nhất rồi thì
each committee can present their findings. The
ban nào ban đấy đưa lên lắm bắt nhá
committee leader cannot proceed without consulting
trưởng ban không được không thông qua
the Dharma leader; that would be against the Six
đạo tràng trưởng như vậy nó không Lục
Harmonies. So, dear fellow practitioners, do you understand this point?
Hòa đâu Thôi quý đầu Hữu rõ chỗ này chưa
We must discuss everything with the Dharma leader, and
ạ phải bàn hết với đạo tràng trưởng Và
even with the committee members, so that
thậm chí bàn cả với ban cán sự nhá Để
everyone has their own
mỗi người có một ý
opinion. Secondly, some practitioners are enthusiastic in their practice and participation in duties,
kiến câu hai ạ việc tu tập tham gia phận
but they listen to and contemplate the
sự nhiệt tình nhưng nghe pháp tư duy
Dharma less, leading to some Buddhists losing heart
pháp ít dẫn đến một số phật tử thối tâm
due to heavy karma. I respectfully ask you, Venerable Master, to explain the
do nghiệp nặng Kính xin cô chỉ dạy lợi
benefits of listening to and contemplating the Dharma in
ích của việc Nghe pháp tư duy pháp tu
practice to transform the mind for each Buddhist practitioner.
tập để chuyển tâm với mỗi phật tử như
Dear fellow
thế nào ạ th Kính thưa quý đạo hữu các
practitioners, do you see
quý Đạo Hữu có thấy chúng ta tu tập cái
how many people transform their karma through the practice of the eighth lesson?
bài số tám không bao nhiêu người chuyển
The eighth lesson is chanting
nghiệp thì cái bài số tám chính là bài
scriptures and listening to Dharma. You
tụng kinh và nghe pháp đấy mà các quý
see, how many families have
Đại Hữu thấy không bao nhiêu gia đình
transformed their karma? I've written on the
người ta chuyển nghiệp Mình viết lên
club's page, and I've seen that no
trang của câu lạc bộ thấy rồi chẳng có
one doesn't listen to the eighth lesson. Therefore,
ai lại không nghe cái bài số tám cả thế
listening to and chanting scriptures both have
cho nên nghe pháp tụng kinh đều có công
merit, so let's not be lazy; it
đức cho nên chúng ta đừng có lười nó
generates blessings to transform
sinh ra phước báo để chuyển hóa
karma. Now, if we don't listen to the Dharma,
nghiệp bây giờ không chị nghe pháp Bây
what can we do?  Therefore,
giờ thì biết làm sao được cho nên chúng
we must listen to the Dharma. There are people whose
ta phải nghe Pháp có những người mà gia
families forbid them from listening, so they have to
đình người ta ngăn cấm quá người ta phải
keep this space and listen to the
tự bạch giữ Hư không này mang đi nghe
Dharma alone, dedicating the merit to the departed
pháp một mình hồi hướng cho các vong
souls. Therefore,
linh đấy các quý đạo hữu ạ Cho nên chúng
we really need merit, so don't be a
ta rất là cần Phước báo cho nên là đừng
practitioner. Have you read the
người tu tập nhá chúng ta đã đọc bài
Sutra of the Hungry Ghosts? Have you listened to the sutra? Even
kinh ngã quỷ Nghe kinh chưa Đấy nó còn
listening to the sutra and the Dharma can lead to enlightenment,
Nghe kinh nghe pháp nó còn được giác ngộ
but we don't listen. Remember, the spirits
mà mình không chịu nghe nhớ này vong
listen through our hearts, not through a radio. If you
linh nó nghe qua tâm mình chứ không phải
open a radio, they won't hear anything,
mở đài Mở đài Nó không nghe thấy gì
but they have a connection with you. If your heart is
nhưng nó có duyên với mình tâm mình giác
enlightened, they will be enlightened. Do you understand
ngộ thì nó giác ngộ có quý đợi Hữu rõ
this point? It's not about relying on the
chỗ này chưa ạ đấy chứ không phải là cứ
radio. What does the radio do? What does it do?
ỷ lại là tôi mở cái đài Mở đài nó làm gì
It listens through your focused mind, your
nghe thế gì nó nghe qua cái tâm chuyên
mind of practice, and that
chú cái tâm tu tập của mình thì làm
transforms them.
chuyển hóa nó nhá
Thirdly, regarding the work in the Dharma hall, the heads of committees
câu ba công việc trong đạo tràng các
discuss things themselves without consulting the head of the Dharma hall.
trưởng ban tự bàn không thông qua đạo
This is unacceptable. Do you
tràng trưởng cái này là không được các
understand this point? All
quý Đạ hiểu rõ chỗ này chưa ạ tất cả các
committees have the opinion of the head of the Dharma hall,
ban bàn đều có ý kiến của đạo tràng
except when the head of the Dharma hall is
trưởng chỉ trừ bao giờ đạo tràng trưởng
busy. Then the head of the Dharma hall can say, "Let's hold a meeting,"
bận thì đạo tràng trưởng bảo là ban họp
but even after the meeting, it must still be approved.
đi nhưng họp xong rồi cũng phải thông
The opinion of the Dharma center leader, esteemed fellow practitioners, is
qua ý kiến của đạo tràng trưởng có Quý
clear to you all. When the Dharma center leader is the
đầi Hữu rõ chưa ạ khi đạo tràng trưởng
head, and we
thì người ta là người đứng đầu mình
don't get their approval, it's like
không thông qua Thế thì khác gì này ở
having a disobedient child in the house.
trong nhà có đứa con hư đâu chưa Nhá
We must get their approval before we can achieve harmony, esteemed fellow
thông qua hết thì chúng ta mới có thể có
practitioners.
được cái hòa hợp được nh các quý đạo hưu
From the Dharma center leader, we also need to get their approval
ạ Từ Đạo tràng trưởng rồi lại còn phải
to the Golden Chrysanthemum Club, so
thông lên câu lạc bộ cúc vàng nữa chứ
we
đâu có phải không đâu cho nên chúng ta
must practice diligently. We must strictly adhere to the
phải cần thực hành tinh Nghiêm nhở lợi
club's regulations and benefits, such as holding
ích và quy định của câu lạc bộ về họp
regular meetings with all Buddhists once a month, and
định kỳ với toàn bộ phật tử một tháng
meetings with the executive committees
một lần còn họp các ban cán sự 1 tháng
twice a month. If we can hold meetings once a month, that would be
Hai lần nếu mà tổ chức họp được 1 tháng
very valuable. Are you all
một lần thì rất là quý thô Quý độu Hữu
clear on this? Focusing on this allows us to
rõ chỗ này chưa ạ thì tập trung vào để
ask each other questions, to show that
chị em còn hỏi han nhau còn biết người
we care, and to have
ta còn thấy mình quan tâm Tức là nó có
mutual exchange and concern.
cái sự trao đổi quan tâm đến nhau nhá
So, the Dharma center leader should try to ensure that
Thế thì đạo tràng trưởng cố gắng làm sao
our Dharma center holds a meeting
để cho đạo tràng mình một tháng họp được
once a month on a fixed day, for example, the
một lần và một cái ngày cố định ví dụ
20th or the 3rd, to listen to Dharma teachings together at the
như ngày 20 hay ngày mùng 3 đến Nghe
Dharma center.  For example, the head of the Dharma hall,
Pháp tập trung nhà đạo tràng trưởng
because of the Dharma, it only manifests after 800 people have finished their
chẳng hạn thì vì pháp thì 800 mới phát
meeting. So, after we've finished our meeting and listened,
mà Thế chúng ta họp xong chúng ta nghe
we disperse, and it
xong rồi thì chúng ta giải tán thì nó nó
becomes a
nó nó nó thành một cái n nó nó nó gắn
cohesive whole within the Dharma, a harmonious coexistence of body, mind, and mind.
kết trong cái Pháp là thân hòa đồng trụ
That's the
ý hòa đồng duyệt đấy các quý Đạ Hữu đấy
harmony of speech and righteousness, which is very good for the Dharma
khẩu hòa vô Chánh nó rất là tốt cho đạo
hall. And if any Dharma hall hasn't been able to
tràng nhá Thế còn nếu đạo tràng nào chưa
organize a meeting yet, try to organize one. If it ca
tổ chức được thì cố gắng tổ chức Còn nếu
n't be organized, then we must hold a meeting on the bus. Do you
không thể tổ chức thì trên xe phải
understand, dear Dharma friends? But
họp Quý đầi Hữu rõ chưa ạ Nhưng mà thực
actually, being able to hold a meeting is the
ra mà nói thì chúng ta họp được là quý
most precious thing. When performing our duties, we need to have a focused and careful mindset.
bóng nhất trong khi làm phận sự cần Khởi
Do we need to concentrate on the
Tâm Như thế nào có cần chuyên chú công
work carefully, or just finish the task?
việc cẩn trọng hay chỉ cần xong việc là
In that offering,
thì trong cái bài cúng dường ấy trước
before the offering, the mind should be pure and
khi cúng thì tâm được
faithful; during the offering, the mind should
gì được Tịnh tín trong khi cúng thì tâm
be joyful and happy, right? Therefore,
được Hoan Hoan Hỉ phải không Thế cho nên
as Buddhists, remember that when we do
là phật tử chúng ta nhớ là chúng ta làm
something, we should do it with
một việc gì thì chúng ta nên làm có tư
thought and observation so that the merit comes from the work
duy có quán sát để từ cái Phước báo nh
we do with our hands. The merit comes from the work we do with our
cái Phước báo là việc ta làm bằng chân
hands. Please understand, not only
tay các quý Đạ hiểu rõ không những lời
our words but also our work, which must be focused and
nói của chúng ta còn công việc nó chuyên
dedicated.  We observe it from beginning to
nhất mà chúng ta quán sát từ đầu đến
end, and it belongs to the realm of observation,
cuối nó xong nó thuộc về trí quán sát
dear friends. Do you understand this point? It
nữa quý đời Hữu rõ chỗ này chưa ạ và nó
also has a merit: when we
cũng có một cái công đức đó là khi ta
receive something, we receive it completely,
được cái gì thì ta được nó viên mãn nó
not a case of "a big beginning and a small ending." When we
không bị đầu voi đuôi chuột quý đ ữu nhá
do something, we should do
trên làm một việc thì chúng ta nên làm
it completely, giving our best effort.
cho nó viên mãn làm hết sức của mình lấy
Wherever we put it, we clean it thoroughly and
cái xong ra ở đâu thì rửa sạch rồi lại
put it back where we finished it. Only then will the work be
cất cái xong ở đấy thì công việc nó mới
complete. It's the same at home.
hoàn thành ở nhà chúng ta cũng thế thôi
We want our children and family to
chúng ta cũng muốn con cái và người nhà
do things exactly as promised. When we go to the
mình làm nó đúng như lời đã hứa mình về
temple, we promise to do this work, but then we mess it up. That's
chùa Mình hứa mình làm công việc này tí
not allowed. So
lại dở Giang thì không được rồi nhá nên
we try to be diligent while practicing
chúng ta cố gắng câu sá trong khi tu học
at Ba Vang Temple or other Dharma groups,
tại chùa Ba Vàng hay các tổ nhóm đạo
or assisting with opening ceremonies or performing our
tràng hoặc đi trợ duyên khai đàn hay
duties. What kind of
công việc phận sự thì việc bàn tán tranh
merit does discussing, debating, or joking at that moment have? And
luận đùa cợt ngay lúc đó sẽ có công đức
how should we practice
như thế nào và cần tu tập như thế nào
correctly and beneficially? Dear
cho đúng pháp và lợi lạc ạ th Kính thưa
friends, when we go to
các quý đạo hữu thế này chúng ta đến bất
anyone's house and help them,
cứ một nhà ai chúng ta hộ người ta cái
this is a very strict and focused observation
này tâm chiếu Hoàn quán rất là nghiêm
because we are sowing seeds of merit for the family.
khắc bởi vì mình gieo duyên cho nhà
People learn the
người ta Người ta học ngay cái tư cách
dignified demeanor of Buddhists, dear fellow practitioners.
oai nghi của người Phật tử các quý đạo
Therefore, when we go there, before
hữu ạ Cho nên khi chúng ta đến đó trước
arriving, we form a group. Today, there are five of us.
khi đến đó là một nhóm Hôm nay là năm
We divide up who will be the master of
người đi chúng ta phân Ai là chủ xám ai
ceremonies, who will play the bell, who will play the wooden clapper, who will play the gong,
chuông Ai mõ ai Khánh ai chủ lễ ai cũng
who will be the main officiant, and who will perform the main ritual. After that, who will
thí thực thế xong rồi thì đến đây thì ai
be the one to sow the seeds of merit for the family and do the
là người gieo Duyên chính cho gia đình
main talk? The others will
nói chuyện chính còn những người kia thì
just sit and listen. Do you understand, dear fellow practitioners?
chỉ ngồi nghe thôi cơ quý đội Hữu rõ
Occasionally,
chưa thỉnh thoảng chỉ thêm vào để nâng
we only add to support the speaker so that things become more enlightened. But if we, as Buddhists, were to gossip and
ta là người phật tử mà chúng ta bàn tán
talk like a marketplace, nothing would bring
nói chuyện như cái chợ ấy thì chả có cái
joy to the people. It would be all
gì mà giúp người ta hoan hỉ với người
over the place,
phật tử được đâu cũng chuyện trên trời
talking
dưới biển nói lung tung cả nói không
indiscriminately, and it wouldn't be good. When we
kiểm soát được thì nó không hay chúng ta
go to someone's house, we should focus solely on
đến nhà chúng ta chỉ chuyên nhất nói về
the work we are doing.
cái việc mà mình đang làm thôi các quý
For example, when we are opening a ceremony for
đạo hu ví dụ đến khai đàn cho nhà người
someone with heavy karma,
ta người ta nặng nghiệp chẳng hạn thì
we should first guide
chúng ta thứ nhất là hướng dẫn cho người
them to strive for progress, and second, present
ta để người ta tinh tấn thứ hai là đưa
examples of families who have
ra các cái gia đình người ta đã chuyển
already transformed their karma and encourage them.  People
nghiệp rồi và động viên cho người ta tu
practice and help others see
tập và giúp cho người ta nhìn thấy
their karma so they can persevere and
nghiệp của mình để kiên trì tinh tấn tu
practice more diligently. It's better than us just talking
tập tốt hơn là chúng ta cứ nói chuyện
nonsense. We're already free from karma, and we
lăng xăng nhà ta đã lặng nghiệp rồi mình
come here gossiping, making others even
đến mình bàn tán vớ vẩn làm cho người ta
more burdened, right? If we speak the
lặng nghiệp thêm phải không Mình có nói
true Dharma, people will change and their
chính Pháp thì người ta chuyển người ta
karma will lighten. But if we keep talking about everything
nhẹ nghiệp đi Còn mình cứ nói chuyện
under the sun, about
trên trời dưới biển chuyện là chuyện
war, protests, politics,
chiến tranh như là chuyện là chuyện biểu
business, and even pointing out
chuyện buôn bán làm ăn lại kể lỗi của
people's faults, then we're even
người này lỗi người kia thế thì thì mình
more burdened than them.
còn lặng nghiệp hơn người ta rồi còn đến
How can we then sow seeds of karma for them?
gieo duyên cho người ta làm sao được các
Do you understand, dear friends? We must be solemn and
quý đầu Hữu rõ chưa mình phải Trang
explain why the monks are here; it's
Nghiêm cứ nói là tại sao các thầy đến nó
because they come with the true
tốt tốt là bởi vì các thầy đến đúng cái
nature of the Sangha, which is purity. So,
tính chất của tăng là thanh tịnh thế cho
when we go to perform rituals, we must try to be solemn. Don't
khi mình đi làm lễ hộ nhá Đừng có bàn
gossip. And secondly,
tán nôi thôi và cái thứ hai nữa là hạn
limit what you eat and drink at the funeral. Do you understand, dear friends?
chế không ăn uống cái gì Ở nhà đám C Quý
Don't eat or drink anything at the funeral;
đội Hữu rõ chưa ạ Đừng có ăn uống cái gì
limit what you eat and drink. People will only say, "
nhà đám hạn chế không người ta chỉ bảo
Yesterday and yesterday, some Buddhist women
đấy hôm nay hôm qua có mấy bà Phật tử
came, and I bought them five kilograms."
đến ấy thì tôi mua cho những năm cân
We gave the women potatoes to eat. Suddenly,
khoai cho các bà ấy ăn ấy thế Tự nhiên
I felt like someone who was chanting scriptures just
mình giống như là cái người đi tụng kinh
to eat. Everyone agrees, right? It
để ăn mọi người thấy đúng không nó giảm
diminishes the noble value of Buddhism.
mất cái giá trị thanh cao của phật pháp
I wasn't hungry. I told my
mình có phải là đói đâu mình dặn luôn
family, "Don't buy anything,
gia đình là các chị đừng mua cái gì
we won't eat it, we'll just drink plain water." "Don't buy anything,
chúng em không ăn đâ em uống nước trắng
we're just here to help the
thôi nhá Đừng mua cái gì chúng em đến hộ
family." Otherwise, you'd see people
gia đình thôi chứ không thì hôm nay thấy
helping others for five days straight.
đi hộ người ta những năm ngày thế Hôm
Today we're treating, tomorrow we're not, and people
nay ta đãi ăn mai ta không có ngườ ta
will feel embarrassed, right? That's why, with the
lại ngại đúng không Thế cho nên là ở với
Buddhists in the Golden Cup Club, the
các phật tử trong câu lạc bộ cốc vàng ấy
Dharma centers are very strict
các đạo tràng là cũng rất tinh Nghiêm
about the eating and drinking at funerals. We don't
trong cái việc ăn uống của nhà đám không
eat or consume the food provided by the
Ăn không Thọ dụng những cái đồ của nhà
funeral, and we tell people, "We're here to
đám nhá và bảo người ta là chúng em đến
help with the pure heart of Buddhism,
giúp với cái tâm thanh tịnh của nhà Phật
hoping for the family to change their karma."
mong mỏi cho gia đình được chuyển nghiệp
Do you understand, fellow practitioners?
thôi đạo hữu rõ chưa ạ
During the day of the Eightfold Path, if you're
nha trong ngày tu bát con trai trong lúc
still discussing worldly matters while listening to the Dharma,
nghe pháp mà vẫn bàn tán việc đời thì có
what kind of merit is that? And how should we practice
công đức thế nào ạ và cần tu tập thế nào
correctly and beneficially? The other day
cho đúng pháp và lợi lạc ạ Hôm trước
we heard about the merit of the Eightfold
chúng ta nghe nghe nói cái công đức bát
Path. If we achieve it on that day,
con trai đấy Nếu ngày hôm đó mà thành
we get eight parts.  The merit is
tựu Được tám Chi phần đấy thì Phước báo
so great that on
nó lớn như thế cho nên là cái ngày hôm
that day, we absolutely must not talk about
đó là chúng ta tuyệt đối không nói
worldly matters, family matters, or anything like that.
chuyện đời không nói chuyện gia đình
We must completely distance ourselves so that
không Chúng ta viễn nii hoàn toàn để
we can fully attain that merit.
chúng ta viên mãn được cái Phước báo chứ
Otherwise, we will waste
không thì Đường nào chúng ta cũng mất
a whole day. On that day, we should only
một ngày ngày hôm đó chúng ta chỉ bàn
discuss the Dharma to
luận về Pháp Thôi để cho mình tăng
increase our wisdom. That's all, dear fellow practitioners.
trưởng trí tuệ Thôi các quý đạo hữu ạ
Discussing the Dharma and encouraging each other
bàn luận về Pháp sách tấn nhau về pháp
is truly essential for those who are practicing the Dharma. The
thật sự là những cái nhà lặng nghiệp nó
merit of cultivating the
rất cần cái cái công đức tu tập của Bát
Eight Precepts is crucial, and while offerings are necessary, we must still practice the Eight Precepts.
Quan Trai giới có cúng dường nhưng vẫn
Therefore, the Eight Precepts are very important.
nên Bát Quan Trai giới rất là quan trọng
We Buddhists should be very strict
các phật tử chúng ta nên tinh Nghiêm
on this day of practice. Regarding
trong một cái ngày tu bắt con trai giới
household matters, when we leave in the morning, we
nhá việc nhà thì lúc đi mình sáng mình
should tell our family, "Today I am going to practice,
đã dặn gia đình hôm nay tôi đi tu rồi
no more contact." But then, "Oh, there are
không có liên lạc nữa chứ còn vậy A có
five kilograms of vegetables, sister, go buy me
năm cân rau đấy chị đi ra chị mua cho em
five kilograms of vegetables, buy me these things," and
năm cân rau đy mua cho em mấy cái này
the phone keeps ringing incessantly. How can that be
cái điện thoại cứ gọi chân chét như thế
called practicing for
Thế thì lế đâu ra gọi là là tu tập một
a day of renunciation and monastic life? The practice of monastic life,
một ngày xả Ly hạnh xuất gia phải không
as the teachers say, "Mom, Mom,
hạnh xuất gia các thầy có lào Mẹ ơi mẹ
Mom, go out!"  That other person is not a child, so
mẹ đi ra ngài kia con gì đâu nhá cho nên
remember that the day of the Eight
chúng ta nhớ là ngày tu Bát Quan Trai
Precepts practice is a day of monastic life practice, that's
giới là chúng ta thực tập xuất gia một
why the merit is so great.
ngày cho nên cái công đức nó mới lớn thế
If we just stay at home, it wo
chứ còn nếu chúng ta cứ tại raia thì nó
n't be enough. So, as Buddhists, we must
không được cho nên phật tử chúng ta phải
do good for ourselves and do good for others. When we
làm tốt cho mình và làm tốt cho người
see people talking, we must
thấy mọi người nói chuyện thì phải nhắc
always remind them that today is a day of practice, so that the
luôn là ngày hôm nay tu bắt con trai các
merit is complete. Everyone needs
công đức vì ai cũng đang rất cần công
merit, and you, dear fellow practitioners, only go for
đức và quý đạo hữu đường nào mới đi đ
one day. If others go for one day and
một ngày thế thì người ta đi một ngày
come back with 10 parts of merit, we
người ta về được 10 phần công đức mình
go for one day and come back with 3 parts.
đi một ngày về được ba phần công đức thế
Isn't that wasteful? We lose it
có phải lãng phí không mà mình lại mất
through gossip and other things, right? So,
đi bằng cách chuyện thị phi chuyện nọ
we
chuyện kia phải không nh chên chúng ta
strive for benefit. When elected to the Executive Committee of the Dharma
gắng lợi ích khi được bầu làm ban CN sự
Hall, we take care of everyone, and then
đạo tràng thì mình lo cho mọi người thì
everyone will take care of us. We should not keep
mình sẽ được mọi người lo cho mình cái
telling people how to be lucky
Phước báo mà cứ bảo người ta làm sao mà
wherever they go. Luck comes from the fact that they
người ta đi đâu cũng may mắn May mắn là
have sown the seeds of
so người đó đã gieo chồng cái công đức
merit for others, right, dear fellow practitioners?
no cho người khác phải không quý đạo hữu
Being in the Executive Committee is very
tro nên làm trong ban cán sự nó rất là
beneficial.  The benefit of caring for others in
lợi ích mình lo cho người khác trong
Buddhism, dear fellow practitioners. The Buddha
Phật pháp các quý đạo hữu ạ Đức phật có
taught that even a thousand years of life is not equal to one
dạy này dù sống ngàn năm không bằng một
day of knowing the Right Path. By sowing the
ngày mà biết tới Chánh Đạo mình gieo
seeds of Buddhism for others,
duyên Phật pháp cho người khác cái Phước
you will receive abundant
báo mở ra cho mình rất là nhiều các quý
blessings. You will have very favorable circumstances
Đạo Hữu sau này mình rất là thuận duyên
in all matters, both in this life and the
trong các cái việc cả kiếp này lẫn kiếp
next. Therefore, the only fear is not having
sau Cho nên chỉ sợ là mình không có
the opportunity to be a leader in Buddhism.
duyên được làm lãnh đạo trong Phật giáo
If you have the opportunity to do so, it's
thôi chứ Mình có duyên mà làm ấy thì là
about supporting the liberation of
cái là mình nâng đỡ sự giải thoát cho
others, not
người cơ mà đâu có phải là cái Phước báo
worldly blessings. Therefore, being on the leadership board
thế gian đâu nhá Cho nên được vào ban
is a very fortunate and
cán sự là một điều rất là may mắn và hy
rare thing. That's why I
hữu và chính như thế cho nên tâm chếu
want to create a separate Dharma center
hoàn quán Muốn tách tách tách thành đạo
so that many people can have
tràng ra để nhiều người được cái duyên
this opportunity to care for
này nhiều người được cái duyên lo cho
others. My master, you alone
mọi người đấy sư phụ nhà mình một mình
have the blessings to care for
sư phụ có cái Phước B báo lo cho mọi
others and see the benefit of sentient beings. In the
người mà thấy lợi ích chúng sinh không
next life, we will continue like this, right?
kiếp sau mình cứ như thế thôi phải không
We know that caring for sentient beings is good.
Mình biết lo cho chúng sinh là tốt mà
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]
[Music]
[âm nhạc]